By now, you know that
a project manager
interacts with their team
members on a daily basis.
What you may not know is
that project managers
are also part of
a bigger ecosystem within their
business or organization.
Projects are not
the only endeavor
a project manager
may participate in.
There are also programs
and portfolios.
A project is one
single-focused endeavor,
a program is a
collection of projects,
and a portfolio is a
collection of projects
and programs across the
whole organization.
Think of it this way: projects
can exist inside of programs,
which can exist
inside of portfolios.
Note that I said "can"
because this won't
always be the case.
Projects can also exist
as separate, unrelated
initiatives.
But if they're a
part of something
bigger within the organization,
projects can become a program.
The collective and
separate successes of
all of these three rely on
continuous improvements.
So who are the people that manage
these various endeavors
and drive success?
Let's think of this
organizationally,
starting with the project manager.
A project manager oversees
individual projects and has
short-term, concrete deliverables.
The project manager
is tasked with
continuously improving
their assigned project.
A program manager
supervises groups of
projects, and even other
project managers,
and focuses on long-term
business objectives.
This program manager
is tasked with
continuously improving
their assigned
collection of projects.
A portfolio manager
supervises a grouping of
projects and programs and
provides centralized
management to them.
This portfolio manager is
tasked with continuously
improving their
assigned collection
of projects and programs.
Different companies may have
slightly different
names for these roles,
but the concept is the same.
Let's examine an instance
where these roles directly
create continuous improvement
for their organizations.
A project manager
has decided to offer
monthly cross-departmental
trainings
to members of their team.
Their team is small, so they
figure it's helpful when people
from other departments understand
their workload and processes.
This way, if someone
is out-of-office,
there will always be coverage.
After a couple months of
these trainings, the
project manager
realizes they not only
improve processes
in communication,
but they act as inadvertent
team-builders.
Because of the trainings,
employees have the opportunity to
interact and to get to
know one another better.
The project manager takes
this info to their
program manager,
and the program manager loves
this unexpected insight.
Now, the program
manager can establish
these trainers across all of
the projects that
they're managing,
making these continuous
improvements program-wide,
rather than
just project-wide.
So exactly what would
projects, programs,
and portfolios look
like at Office Green?
Getting the Plant Pals service
launched and running is a project.
It's short-term and temporary.
Once a service is launched
successfully, the project ends.
Keeping the service
going indefinitely
requires the project
to become a program.
The program—running
the Plant Pals
service—becomes one of
Office Green's long-term
business objectives,
and the company will work
on continuously
improving the program.
Now Plant Pals, along
with other projects and
programs at Office Green, are
included in the
company's portfolio.
As continuous improvements are
executed in Project
Plant Pals,
the program and portfolios and
Office Green will notice
the benefits of that.
For instance, let's refer to
the example of overstocked plants
from the previous video.
Well, using PDCA—plan,
do, check, act—you
notice a drop in
the sales of one of
the plant varieties.
So you decide to
reorganize the website so
the species that isn't selling
is featured at the top,
giving a small discount.
This change is so
successful that you
end up making it a best practice.
From now on, low-performing
and overstocked plant varieties
will be featured at the
top of the website.
This is, in fact, a new process.
Running it over and over again
will drive continuous
improvements.
The continuous
improvement you made to
the project reflected well in
your program and portfolio,
because now that
that it's been tested,
the same strategy
can be implemented
company-wide for all of
the company's other
sites and products,
reducing waste and increasing
revenue across the board.
If many or all of the projects
at Office Green see
the same improvement,
that directly
benefits the program,
which is the collective
of the projects.
If the same strategy is
applied to programs
at Office Green,
the portfolio will
directly benefit by having
stronger indicators
for profitability.
Now we've learned how to define
a program and how it
differs from a project.
We've also discussed the impact
of a project that could
result in a program.
And we learned how a project can turn
into programs or portfolios.
Now that you know more about how
these three concepts
work together,
let's head to the next video.